<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Warp-Woof-Wimble</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/</id><updated>2016-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Reflections on and in "A Pin-light, Bent"</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/11/16/reflections-on-and-in-a-pin-light-bent/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-11-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-11-16:blog/2016/11/16/reflections-on-and-in-a-pin-light-bent/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/pages/a-pin-light-bent/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; has the barest of arrangements of any song from &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, it is the cycle&amp;rsquo;s only solo: the only musician credited in the liner notes is Joanna Newsom, on harp and vocals, and the recording features none of that chorus of multiplied Newsoms heard elsewhere on the album. The song is a soliloquy, where a flight attendant mourns her slow rise and wonders at her slow fall, before she dies &amp;ldquo;anelectric and alone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that respect, the song is one of vulnerability. But it begins with an undeniable humour. Consider the first two stanzas (up to the line, &amp;ldquo;Poor flight attendant&amp;rdquo;): the lines, which are each a single sentence, are somewhere between terse and pithy. They have a dense rhyme scheme, where each line in a stanza rhymes and always with that &lt;em&gt;lie&lt;/em&gt; sound as its second syllable. Such patterns bring to mind nonsense rhymes, not the elegy that the words&amp;rsquo; sense implies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallelism of these lines further enhances the sense of irreverence: &amp;ldquo;My life comes and goes,&amp;rdquo; in the first stanza (S1) changes in S2 to, &amp;ldquo;My life came and went,&amp;rdquo; implying that the end of the narrator&amp;rsquo;s existence is as inconsequential as changing two words in a song. The &amp;ldquo;short flight&amp;rdquo;, which in S1 we take to be a trip by aeroplane, in S2 becomes a freefall. And perhaps the &amp;ldquo;rows&amp;rdquo; of S1 is a pun (on &lt;em&gt;rose&lt;/em&gt;) made in contrast to the &amp;ldquo;descent&amp;rdquo; that takes its place in S2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repetitive, measured metre of the lyrics is reflected by the measured, repetitive harp accompaniment. In the first two stanzas, the harmony line is just two alternating notes, underlying which is a very simple bassline that serves barely to suggest the chord of the proceeding few bars. When the metre of the lyrics changes in S3, so too does the accompaniment, with arpeggiated chords heard in a rhythm working against the primary (musical) metre. The melody line becomes more drawn out. The lyrics remain repetitive, but in a different manner now, one that leads us less to look for wordplay and more to consider gravely every word that is sung.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the sky, over the &lt;strong&gt;ocean&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;br /&gt;
And the &lt;strong&gt;ocean&lt;/strong&gt;, skirting the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;city&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;br /&gt;
And the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;city&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, bright as a &lt;strong&gt;garden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(when the &lt;strong&gt;garden&lt;/strong&gt; woke to meet me),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this mood doesn&amp;rsquo;t last long. After the first four lines of S3, the song returns to the pattern of the initial stanzas. The rhymes return (including rather contrived-sounding double rhymes this time: &amp;ldquo;honeycomb&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;funny homes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;intersected&amp;rdquo; with &amp;ldquo;anelectric&amp;rdquo;) and while there is no wordplay that I can see, there&amp;rsquo;s still that word &amp;ldquo;funny&amp;rdquo;, reminding us not to afford our narrator too much respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a whole, the third stanza has, to my mind, the greatest resonance with the themes of the album. There is sky and sea (&amp;ldquo;Goose Eggs&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Divers&amp;rdquo;); there is a garden (&amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;rdquo;); there is a city (&amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Leaving the City&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Same Old Man&amp;rdquo;); altogether, there is the zoomed-out view of Earth from &amp;ldquo;My Heart Alive&amp;rdquo; (and indeed from Kim Keever&amp;rsquo;s floral, submarine skyscapes that illustrate the album cover and liner notes); there is sightseeing and home; and, of course, there is light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere,&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; it has been suggested that &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; follows a chiastic structure &amp;ndash; that is to say, a structure based on the figure of speech known as chiasmus, where the order the terms in the first of two parallel clauses is reversed in the second. Such a form encourages symmetry and recapitulation &amp;ndash; re-casting old ideas in new light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most beautiful examples of this form that I have come across in modern poetry, which also happens to be one of the most technically accomplished, is by Julia Copus, entitled &lt;a href="http://www.poetryarchive.org/poem/back-seat-my-mothers-car"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Back Seat of My Mother&amp;rsquo;s Car&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It has a perhaps more refined form of symmetry than chiasmus and I would encourage you to read it before continuing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an introduction to the poem, Copus said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole poem takes place over a few seconds. &amp;hellip;
It&amp;rsquo;s written in a new form which I developed while
I was writing my first book. The form is called
&amp;lsquo;Specular&amp;rsquo;, after the Latin for a &amp;lsquo;mirror&amp;rsquo; &amp;hellip; .
Here the car window acts as a reflecting device
in the middle of the poem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the strength of the poem lies largely in the way Copus marries so naturally its &amp;ldquo;specular&amp;rdquo; form with the &lt;em&gt;verbal&lt;/em&gt; reflector of &amp;ldquo;cool slick glass&amp;rdquo; mentioned at the point of inflexion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One could argue that &amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;rdquo; also has such an inflexion. If only there were one more (short-lined) verse at the end of the song! Then the rhymes, the metres and the dynamics would invert perfectly around the 2m:21s mark, at the melody&amp;rsquo;s rest between &amp;ldquo;alone&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;in&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nevertheless, it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting way to read the song. S4 introduces two delineating elements: firstly, the &amp;ldquo;fence&amp;rdquo;, then, later on, the &amp;ldquo;mirror&amp;rdquo;. These are, perhaps, hints at a specular structure &amp;ndash; like the &amp;ldquo;cool slick glass&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ldquo;My Mother&amp;rsquo;s Car&amp;rdquo;. (I&amp;rsquo;ve reproduced the &amp;ldquo;long metre&amp;rdquo; part below for comparison with the corresponding part of S3. By this analysis, the structure corresponds a mirror with Amora.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;from the Great Light that shines through a &lt;strong&gt;pin&lt;/strong&gt;-hole,&lt;br /&gt;
when the &lt;strong&gt;pin&lt;/strong&gt;-light calls itself &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selfhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;,&lt;br /&gt;
and the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Selfhood&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; inverts on &lt;strong&gt;a mirror&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
in an &lt;strong&gt;Amora&lt;/strong&gt; Obscura.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let us reflect again on the echoes of other parts of &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;. Earlier, I matched the view of Earth in S3 with that heard in &amp;ldquo;My Heart Alive&amp;rdquo;, but I neglected to point out an important distinction: the latter song has the narrator ascending &amp;ndash; watching the pale blue dot get further and further away &amp;ndash; whereas here the direction is reversed: she is decidedly coming back down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the resonances I hear in S4 are with those less happy parts of the album than those in S3: there is a divide (&amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Divers&amp;rdquo;, the trenches of &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;); there is attendance &amp;ndash; in the sense of waiting (the forgotten Twenty Thousand in &amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo;, the women left waiting in &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Divers&amp;rdquo;, this song&amp;rsquo;s unlucky narrator); there is cruel defenselessness (&amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Leaving the City&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;My Heart Alive&amp;rdquo;); even light is portrayed as an unfriendly juggernaught, (see, especially, &amp;ldquo;Leaving the City&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;rdquo;), and the final word of the stanza is &amp;ldquo;darkened&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S5 echoes, primarily, the first and second stanzas, in terms not only of its rhyme and structure but also its sentiment. The narrator talks again of her life, her death, and the small freedoms found between the two. Yet the tone has darkened; we aren&amp;rsquo;t laughing any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also find the song&amp;rsquo;s second echo of &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;. This echo is stronger than the others, and is of a sort found often in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;: namely, the call-and-response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, the nightjar calls,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, inasmuch as that light is loaned,&lt;br /&gt;
and, insofar as we&amp;rsquo;ve borrowed bones,&lt;br /&gt;
must every debt now be repaid&lt;br /&gt;
in star-spotted, sickle-winged night raids?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, in &amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;rdquo;, the flight attendant responds,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s mine. Or, at least, it&amp;rsquo;s lent.&lt;br /&gt;
And my life, until the time is spent&lt;br /&gt;
is a pin-light bent.&lt;br /&gt;
It&amp;rsquo;s a pin-light, bent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would be a fitting way to end the album, yet I believe that the form of the song implies its consequent. As mentioned earlier, the structure indicates symmetry, but Newsom chooses to cut the natural conclusion, bringing to song to an abrupt end. We could, therefore, consider the next track as a continuation of the thoughts of &amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of narrative, this song is notably similar to James Dickey&amp;rsquo;s poem, &amp;ldquo;Falling&amp;rdquo;, and, while their forms differ significantly, each has a distinctive structure that serves to inform the meaning of the work.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Perhaps, like Dickey&amp;rsquo;s air stewardess (who, during the ultimate freedom afforded by death, undresses as she falls), Newsom&amp;rsquo;s narrator breaks free of the trammels of her origins to express herself &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;unmarked&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;unmoored&amp;rdquo;, and at last taken seriously &amp;ndash; in the following track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fromamouth.com/milkymoon/viewtopic.php?f=58&amp;amp;t=1391"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Divers&amp;rsquo; ring composition: sources of inspiration and meaning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The layout of the lyrics in the &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; lyric booklet obscures the essential structure of the last three lines of S3, which are sung as four: &amp;ldquo;from that height was a honeycomb / made of light from those funny homes, / intersected: each enclosed, / anelectric and alone.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dickey: &amp;ldquo;I was interested in using the kind of time-telescoping effect that Bergson talks about in discussing the difference between clock time and lived time. It takes twenty minutes to read the poem, more or less. It surely wouldn’t have taken her nearly that long to fall. But as to how long it seemed to her, that’s quite a different thing.&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="http://www.english.illinois.edu/maps/poets/a_f/dickey/falling.htm"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>High days, holidays, hejiras: travelling through Divers</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/09/25/high-days-holidays-hejiras-travelling-through-divers/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-09-25:blog/2016/09/25/high-days-holidays-hejiras-travelling-through-divers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This piece explores the theme of travel running throughout &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;, recently highlighted by a &lt;a href="http://allthebirds.tumblr.com/post/149510193303/delving-into-divers-the-title-song"&gt;recent post&lt;/a&gt; at Blessing All the Birds and &lt;a href="https://medium.com/@hexagn/joanna-newsoms-word-of-warning-9b26e5c131cf"&gt;also explored&lt;/a&gt; by Michael Hicks. However, I want to introduce it by talking about the Joni Mitchell album, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://jonimitchell.com/music/album.cfm?id=10"&gt;Hejira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Every song on that album relates to travelling or sight-seeing in one way or another &amp;mdash; including mentions of New York City, aeroplane flights, and diving birds &amp;mdash; yet Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s recounted travels are not often happy ones, hence the title, which is defined as an &amp;ldquo;exodus or departure&amp;rdquo; (OED).&lt;sup id="fnref:9"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:9" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of my favourite songs from the album, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://jonimitchell.com/music/song.cfm?id=118"&gt;Amelia&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Mitchell waxes melancholy on aeroplanes, after seeing contrails up above that remind her of that object that took her all over the world, namely her acoustic guitar. The song is named after Amelia Earhart (1897-1937), the quintessential celebrity aviatrice, who was an icon for many women in her lifetime.&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Sadly, Earhart disappeared over the Pacific Ocean during an attempted circumnavigation, becoming what the song describes as &amp;ldquo;a ghost of aviation&amp;rdquo;. At the end of each verse, Mitchell assures Earhart: &amp;ldquo;Amelia, it was just a false alarm.&amp;rdquo; But Mitchell is ill at ease with travelling, and this reassurance is just as much directed at herself. She&amp;rsquo;s worried that she has too much in common with Earhart, and, like a modern-day Icarus, will be &amp;ldquo;swallowed by the sky&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Looking back on this album today, the comparison seems even more apt. Each of these determined people was a pioneer in her time &amp;mdash; as a woman &amp;mdash; but was also hugely influential in her own right. Luckily, Mitchell has not yet disappeared somewhere over the Pacific Ocean.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this attitude, the album ends with Mitchell finding &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;refuge&lt;/em&gt; in the roads&amp;rdquo; (of which more later). This conclusion is foreshadowed in a verse of &amp;ldquo;Amelia&amp;rdquo; that exposes her curiosity even while she criticises those who succumb to theirs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People will tell you where they&amp;rsquo;ve gone&lt;br /&gt;
They&amp;rsquo;ll tell you where to go&lt;br /&gt;
But till you get there yourself you never really know&lt;br /&gt;
Where some have found their paradise&lt;br /&gt;
Others just come to harm&lt;br /&gt;
Oh, Amelia, it was just a false alarm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tension, or ambiguity, between curiosity and ignorance, between the novel and the familiar, is also found, rarefied, in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My last essay examined some of the nature of time and history in the album, and it is important not to forget the analogous theme of space and travel. For there are not just many geographical settings in the album, but also many acts of travelling. Some of these are tabulated below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Track title&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Modes of transport&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Anecdotes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Horseback, flight*, wheel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sapokanikan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Foot, aeroplane*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Leaving the City&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Horseback, boat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Goose Eggs&lt;sup id="fnref:10"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:10" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bus, train, foot, aeroplane&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Waltz of the 101st Lightborne&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Spaceship, foot&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The Things I Say&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Divers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Swimming*, boat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Same Old Man&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Barrel, freefall* (leaf)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;You Will Not Take My Heart Alive&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Flight*, train, foot&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A Pin-Light, Bent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Flight, freefall*&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Time, As a Symptom&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Almost all of the above!&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*) = diving implied&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act is sometimes a hejira:&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; think the narrators of &amp;ldquo;Leaving the City&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Same Old Man&amp;rdquo; making a new home away from New York City, or the subject of &amp;ldquo;Goose Eggs&amp;rdquo;, who is reminded, &amp;ldquo;You had somewhere that you had to go.&amp;rdquo; Within individual songs, we often get both sides of the coin: &lt;em&gt;hejira&lt;/em&gt; against &lt;em&gt;home&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo; begins with a broken soldier slung over a horse&amp;rsquo;s back and ends with a daughter being called for supper. &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;s infantryman realises his mistake in taking up arms and remembers being &amp;ldquo;lashed to the prow&amp;rdquo;; but the end of the song &lt;a href="http://allthebirds.tumblr.com/post/142261145623/lowlands-away-and-waltz-of-the-101st"&gt;evokes a traditional shanty&lt;/a&gt; told by a woman waiting on the shore. The last observation of &amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;s free-falling air hostess is the &amp;ldquo;light from those funny homes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other places, the journeys are akin to the travellers&amp;rsquo; tales found in tracks from &lt;em&gt;Hejira&lt;/em&gt; such as &amp;ldquo;Song for Sharon&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Furry Sings the Blues&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; breathless accounts illustrated by mementoes unstuck in time and space.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;rdquo; has this, where Newsom boasts, &amp;ldquo;And you can barely tell, if I guard it well, / Where I have been, and seen, / Pristine, unfelled.&amp;rdquo; In &amp;ldquo;The Things I Say&amp;rdquo;, Newsom names, in a tourist-like manner, &amp;ldquo;Paris, France&amp;rdquo;, and reminds a subject of the time he framed a dancing girl with his hands &amp;mdash; a sort of holiday snap. Mitchell rails against these fragmented memories in &amp;ldquo;Amelia&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drone of flying engines&lt;br /&gt;
Is a song so wild and blue&lt;br /&gt;
It scrambles time and seasons if it gets thru to you&lt;br /&gt;
Then your life becomes a travelogue&lt;br /&gt;
Of picture-postcard-charms&lt;br /&gt;
Amelia, it was just a false alarm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newsom, I feel, reveals a similar ambivalence; consider, for example, &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, where she tells us,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what is this sample proving?&lt;br /&gt;
Anecdotes cannot say what Time may do.&lt;br /&gt;
[&amp;hellip;]&lt;br /&gt;
Now hush, little babe.&lt;br /&gt;
You don&amp;rsquo;t want to be&lt;br /&gt;
down in the trenches&lt;br /&gt;
remembering with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journeys seem to continue from track to track, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The diver of the title song leaves his wife on the pier while he traverses the &amp;ldquo;arid world&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Before leaving, he gave her a jewel, which his wife cruelly jests is &amp;ldquo;worth twice this woman&amp;rsquo;s life&amp;rdquo;. She hopes he&amp;rsquo;ll return with a pearl for a souvenir. In the meantime, she knows she must bide her time, questioning her travelling counterpart in his absence. &amp;ldquo;How do you choose your life?&amp;rdquo;, she wonders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next track, &amp;ldquo;Same Old Man&amp;rdquo;, the narrator&amp;rsquo;s journey is over, and this one too stays where she is. A leaf falls from a tree &amp;mdash; spring turns to autumn while she sings an elegy to reliability, in a cover version of a traditional folk song. That minimoog bassline starts up in the third verse, grounding the listener alongside words that rejoice over leaving the Apple: &amp;ldquo;New York City won&amp;rsquo;t see me again. [&amp;hellip;] I&amp;rsquo;m certainly glad to be at home,&amp;rdquo; says she, yet, 30 seconds hence, in &amp;ldquo;My Heart Alive&amp;rdquo;, the curiosity of the narrator begins anew. &amp;ldquo;And what do you remember most? / The line of the sea, seceding the coast?&amp;rdquo; She&amp;rsquo;s envious of this person who &amp;ldquo;severed all strings&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Hejira&lt;/em&gt;&amp;lsquo;s penultimate track, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://jonimitchell.com/music/song.cfm?id=68"&gt;Blue Motel Room&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, Mitchell initiates a futile bargain with her wayward lover: &amp;ldquo;You lay down your sneaking round the town, honey, / And I&amp;rsquo;ll lay down the highway.&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; &amp;ldquo;You will not take my heart alive,&amp;rdquo; Newsom asserts, and it sounds just as shaky. Twice, her vocals and harp climb from a comfortable middle pitch to the highest reach of their ranges, before queueing and diving back down. Newsom is on the move. She goes into battle. Then, in counterpoint to her question in &amp;ldquo;Divers&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;How do you choose your form?&amp;rdquo;), she rises &amp;ldquo;to take [her] shape at last&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;I won&amp;rsquo;t come round this way again,&amp;rdquo; she tells us proudly, as her home moves further and further away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The zooming-out from Earth conjured at the end of &amp;ldquo;My Heart Alive&amp;rdquo; (and the beginning of the following song, &amp;ldquo;A Pin-light, Bent&amp;rdquo;) matches the concluding lines of &lt;em&gt;Hejira&lt;/em&gt;, from the song, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://jonimitchell.com/music/song.cfm?id=7"&gt;Refuge of the Roads&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a highway service station&lt;br /&gt;
Over the month of June&lt;br /&gt;
Was a photograph of the earth&lt;br /&gt;
Taken coming back from the moon&lt;br /&gt;
And you couldn&amp;rsquo;t see a city&lt;br /&gt;
On that marbled bowling ball&lt;br /&gt;
Or a forest or a highway&lt;br /&gt;
Or me here least of all&lt;br /&gt;
You couldn&amp;rsquo;t see these cold water restrooms&lt;br /&gt;
Or this baggage overload&lt;br /&gt;
Westbound and rolling&lt;br /&gt;
Taking refuge in the roads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This flight fulfills at last the desire, first expressed in &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, to go &amp;ldquo;where where the dew won&amp;rsquo;t dry / [&amp;hellip;] where the light won&amp;rsquo;t bend.&amp;rdquo; She is at lofty heights, in the perfect place for the philosophising heard throughout the final two tracks. Like Mitchell says in her concluding song: &amp;ldquo;And it made most people nervous / They just didn&amp;rsquo;t want to know / What I was seeing in the refuge of the roads.&amp;rdquo;[^8]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And like that, I think we see clearly how beautifully the themes of each song on &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; dovetail. Look at the questions posed in &amp;ldquo;The Things I Say&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;What happened to the man you were[&amp;hellip;]? Did he die, or does that man endure, somewhere far away?&amp;rdquo; By the ending of the album, Newsom is that man: as flight attendant, she plunges to her death; yet she stands brave, and holds on through &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;&amp;lsquo; freewheeling finale, until the cycle begins again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:9"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This meaning comes from the word&amp;rsquo;s primary definition: &amp;ldquo;The flight of Muhammad from Mecca to Medina in 622 A.D.&amp;rdquo;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:9" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a detailed biography of Earhart as an annotation to the &lt;a href="http://jonimitchell.com/music/song.cfm?id=118"&gt;song&amp;rsquo;s lyrics on Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that Mitchell had just turned 33 when the album was released in 1972: the same age as Newsom at the release of &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:10"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;taking a bus, to take a train and just plain vamoose&amp;rdquo; cf. &amp;ldquo;I took a ferry to the highway / Then I drove to a pontoon plane / I took a plane to a taxi / And a taxi to a train&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Black Crow&amp;rdquo;)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:10" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newsom has often said in interviews how she dislikes touring and is happiest at home. &lt;a href="http://www.lesinrocks.com/2015/11/05/musique/joanna-newsom-la-musique-est-toujours-une-histoire-damour-11784470/"&gt;One example&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on this, see my previous essay: &lt;a href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/09/06/unstuck-in-time-narratives-of-war-in-divers/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Unstuck in Time&amp;rdquo;: Narratives of War in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I struggle here to understand what is meant exactly by &amp;ldquo;to count your way across the depths&amp;rdquo;. Perhaps he counts the waves, or pearls, as he walks. Or perhaps he tells stories. One definition of &amp;ldquo;to count&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;to esteem, account, reckon, regard, hold (a thing) to be (so and so)&amp;rdquo; (OED)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>"Unstuck in time": Narratives of war in Divers</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/09/06/unstuck-in-time-narratives-of-war-in-divers/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-06T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-09-06:blog/2016/09/06/unstuck-in-time-narratives-of-war-in-divers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2016, the centenary year of the Somme offensive, one finds the influence of the Great War on modern culture impossible to ignore. Today, a popular belief is that we know far more now about the war and its causes than most of the men who lost their lives in its enactment. Yet our knowledge is distorted &amp;mdash; obscured by dust thrown up by the march of time, and gleaned largely from history books written by the victors. Such is the setting in which I here consider Joanna Newsom&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violence and conflict are common in Newsom&amp;rsquo;s lyrics. Rebecca Varley&amp;ndash;Winter noted that &amp;ldquo;[her] lyrics are full of violent metaphors&amp;hellip; her songs bristle with bombs, armies constantly in defeat, her soliders always dying.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;, this imagery is more often put to ends of narrative rather than metaphor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/pages/sapokanikan/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, the blood has already been spilled. In the guise of omniscient narrator, Newsom gives us a guided tour of historical Greenwich Village, where we read inscriptions on rusty monuments and hear a rag to the &amp;ldquo;Brave Men and Women&amp;rdquo; of WWII. Meanwhile, to the 20 000 whose cause for death is forgotten, we might as well be singing &amp;ldquo;Tramp the Dirt Down&amp;rdquo;. This tour is reliable &amp;mdash; based on newspaper clippings and commemorative plaques &amp;mdash; yet it is as dry and lifeless as the lone and level sands of Shelley&amp;rsquo;s sonnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/pages/anecdotes/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; gets us closer to violence with its recollection of battles past. Trenches, night raids, and &amp;ldquo;sending the first scouts over [the top]&amp;rdquo; all bring to mind the conflict on the Western Front. Supporting this story is a military cast; the narrator is perhaps an officer sharing a joke with his deputy, Nightjar, in the silent moon-light. He, our officer, makes poetry of what he sees, preserving in song an anecdote from his time &amp;ldquo;down in the trenches&amp;rdquo;; in contrast to the official records examined in &amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo; is, like something written by Wilfred Owen or Siegfried Sassoon, as much a work of art as a battle diary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the themes of the song, I find a poem by Great War veteran Ivor Gurney particularly fitting. In &lt;a href="https://www.poetryfoundation.org/poems-and-poets/poems/detail/57248"&gt;&amp;ldquo;After-Glow&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, he recalls a time when, in the nocturnal silence of the trenches,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition lyrics"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time passed from mind. Time died; and then we were&lt;br /&gt;
Once more at home together, you and I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, the poem begins in the front-line, passing through a period of reminiscence before ending in a domestic scene. (The poem also has an aspect of rusted monument, being dedicated to Gurney&amp;rsquo;s friend and fellow-soldier F. W. Harvey, at the time feared dead.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo; is more allegorical than &amp;ldquo;After-Glow&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, the former was written by Newsom &amp;mdash; herself no veteran &amp;mdash; and at times it verges on science-fiction. Time stops like it did for Gurney, but ideas of time-travel (&amp;ldquo;temporal infidelity&amp;rdquo;) and the bending of light link the song with Albert Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theories of relativity and those theories&amp;rsquo; employment in the plots of many a sci-fi novel. Consider the soldiers of &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;: a cavalry of nightjar-oids? That would follow the tradition of sci-fi writers who take their cues from nature gone grotesque &amp;mdash; its pages are filled with hive-minded ants the size of cars, chameleons that change form as well as colour, and mechanical men with twice our strength and half our compassion. Like the politically charged poems of the war poets, this is something other than a sober history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/pages/waltz-of-the-101st-lightborne/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Waltz of the 101st Lightborne&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is another war story. But hang on, has this fight happened yet? It certainly began some time in the future (see reference to a fourth world war in line 3), but, in &amp;ldquo;eternal return and repeat&amp;rdquo;, it seems to have looped round to the golden age of the United States Pacific Seaboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of jumping along the timeline of history &amp;mdash; heard here and elsewhere in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; reminds me of Billy Pilgrim, a (fictional) WWII veteran who believes he has become &amp;ldquo;unstuck in time&amp;rdquo;. Pilgrim is the protagonist of Kurt Vonnegut&amp;rsquo;s semi-autobiographical novel, &lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse-Five&lt;/em&gt;, and through the book Vonnegut implies that his jumble of vicarious anecdotes of the war and science-fictional flights of fancy are no less than the only way he can describe what he saw. So, too, Newsom in &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt;. (&amp;ldquo;The whole record is personal, but a lot of what is most personal is conveyed through pure fiction, or, sometimes, even science-fiction.&amp;rdquo;)&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; is well described as a &amp;ldquo;stack of slides&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; two-dimensional, translucent things which, taken on their own, depict clear forms; yet these aural sheets of celluloid can be overlaid, obscuring the especial details of each while (in strong enough light) each layer makes the common parts clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when we stack these three songs (&amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;), what&amp;rsquo;s left after the debridement? At first glance, they follow the time-honoured schema of &amp;ldquo;past, present, future&amp;rdquo;. Or perhaps we should take cues from a former US Secretary of Defence. Speaking of the USA&amp;rsquo;s military intelligence concerning the weapons capabilities of Iraq (shortly before his country invaded theirs), Donald Rumsfeld popularised another trio: the (un)known (un)knowns. So, &amp;ldquo;Anecdotes&amp;rdquo; comes to us from the well-documented Great War (a known known); &amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo; acknowledges the lost kingdom of Ozymandias and its modern equivalents (known unknowns all); while &amp;ldquo;Waltz&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; is pure, fantastical speculation &amp;mdash; the history of the future will always be an unknown unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In combination, these songs make us question accepted narratives of war. Why do we commemorate the wars we do? What have we forgotten? Are anecdotes of WWI any more reliable than those of WWIV?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever the battles of &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; take place, Newsom clearly intends to tell us the human stories. In a work that features so much war, there are very few war machines &amp;mdash; no laser guns, no spaceships. No atom bombs. One recalls Einstein&amp;rsquo;s creed: &amp;ldquo;I know not with what weapons World War III will be fought, but World War IV will be fought with sticks and stones.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this train of thought, we return to &amp;ldquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rdquo; and the only victim of war namechecked in the album: John Purroy Mitchel. In a song stuffed with a plethora of historical references, it is notable that Mitchel&amp;rsquo;s potted biography takes almost half of the recording to recount. Newsom chooses to immortalise in verse this &amp;ldquo;boy&amp;rdquo; who deserves the honour just as much as any casualty of the Western Front. Leading by example, she shows that, while &amp;ldquo;the event is in the hand of God&amp;rdquo;, its legacy is in that one of whoever tells its story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/World_War_III"&gt;Quote on Wikiquote&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1687/"&gt;Relevant XKCD&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://glasgowreviewofbooks.com/2015/12/10/lyric-mediums-joanna-newsoms-divers/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lyric Mediums: Joanna Newsom&amp;rsquo;s Divers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, Glasgow Review of Books, December 2015&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.thefader.com/2015/10/19/joanna-newsom-divers-interview"&gt;Fader, October 2015&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Whatever happened to the "Good Intentions" music video?</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/08/25/whatever-happened-to-the-good-intentions-music-video/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-08-25:blog/2016/08/25/whatever-happened-to-the-good-intentions-music-video/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many Joanna Newsom fans will have heard of the &amp;ldquo;Good Intentions Paving Company&amp;rdquo; music video, which was promoted following the release of &lt;em&gt;Have One On Me&lt;/em&gt;, but has not to date seen a full airing. According to user &amp;lsquo;hanahstar&amp;rsquo; on the Milky Moon forums, the video was filmed in Hungary in 2010 or early 2011. Around April 2011, Karni &amp;amp; Saul (K&amp;amp;S) were revealed as the directors. Stills from the video, and some behind-the-scenes shots, were released by K&amp;amp;S in June. In December, a minute-long excerpt of the video was released. (As of writing, this is still available on K&amp;amp;S&amp;rsquo;s Vimeo channel. The photos are also easy to find on the &amp;lsquo;net.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ensuing silence, several fans contacted entities associated with the video in order to try and find out what had happened to it. To the best of my knowledge, the closest thing to an official statement gleaned was the following, purportedly posted on K&amp;amp;S&amp;rsquo;s Tumblr around November 2012 and since deleted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;dear Joanna fans who have been writing to us.first of all yes the video for good intentions was commissioned by drag city and finished. we are very proud of it.and everyone who sees it absolutely loves it.for various reasons that are not up to us drag city will not release this video.we are gutted.and apologies for letting anyone down.we believe it is a fab piece of film.and maybe one day it will see the light.thanks for your kind emails and for following us.best karni and saul&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to another forum post, Ryan Francesconi, who was a key member of personnel for the song, also commented on the video, saying it &amp;ldquo;didn&amp;rsquo;t turn out exactly right&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s all I could find out!&lt;sup id="fnref:source"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:source" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If anyone reading this can contribute any more puzzle pieces, please get in touch. Newsom&amp;rsquo;s label, Drag City, generally seems to have a very patient, artist-focussed management with very deep pockets, which, to my mind, makes a nixing by Newsom more likely an explanation than any financial or legal threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:source"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post was pieced together mainly from a Milky Moon forum thread, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://www.fromamouth.com/milkymoon/viewtopic.php?f=23&amp;amp;t=359"&gt;new video for joanna&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. Retrospective thanks goes to all the forum users who pursued this, and who quoted statements rather than just linking to (now irrecoverable) posts on social media websites.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:source" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="have-one-on-me"></category><category term="good-intentions-paving-company"></category><category term="music-video"></category></entry><entry><title>'Books and more' update</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/08/17/books-and-more-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-08-17:blog/2016/08/17/books-and-more-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just added some extra details to the site content ahead of a few longer pieces that are in the works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="changelog"&gt;Changelog&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added a few items to the &amp;lsquo;Books and more&amp;rsquo; page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Noted another Kim Keever interview on the &amp;lsquo;Divers&amp;rsquo; album page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small additions to the pages for &amp;lsquo;Sapokanikan&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;Divers (album)&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Only Skin&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Warp-Woof-Wimble is launched (in flight)</title><link href="http://www.warpwoofwimble.com/blog/2016/06/24/warp-woof-wimble-is-launched-in-flight/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-24T00:00:00+01:00</published><author><name>Rufous Nightjar</name></author><id>tag:www.warpwoofwimble.com,2016-06-24:blog/2016/06/24/warp-woof-wimble-is-launched-in-flight/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;And&amp;hellip; here we go! The site is very much in a draft stage, and I welcome corrections and additions. Comments are turned on below blog posts for now, and my email address is in the sidebar. Please bear with me if &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m&lt;/em&gt; offline for weeks at a time over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the changelog, but first a few words on the origin of this place: the impetus for the site came with my realisation some weeks ago that, on the internet, there is no definitive compilation of interviews, reviews and criticism related to the works of Joanna Newsom. I begun by collecting URLs to relevant items on a Pinboard account (linked in the sidebar). I then teased some threads out of the collection in order to create the pages of this site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="changelog"&gt;Changelog&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="additions"&gt;Additions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notes for &lt;em&gt;Divers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Ys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of books etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of interviews&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary></entry></feed>